My father was, I am sure, intended by nature to be a cheerful, kindly man.
我敢肯定，造化本意是要我父亲做个快活、和善的人。
Until he was thirty-four years old he worked as a farmhand for a man named Thomas Butterworth whose place lay near the town of Bidwell.
直到三十四岁，他都在给一个名叫托马斯·巴特沃思的人当农场帮工，那人的农场就在比德韦尔镇附近。
He had then a horse of his own and on Saturday evenings drove into town to spend a few hours in social intercourse with other farmhands.
那时他有一匹自己的马，每逢星期六傍晚便赶车进城，花上几个钟头同别的农场帮工交际往来。
In town he drank several glasses of beer and stood about in Ben Head’s saloon—crowded on Saturday evenings with visiting farmhands.
他在镇上会喝上几杯啤酒，在本·黑德的酒馆里闲站着——每到星期六晚上，那里都挤满了进城来的农场帮工。
Songs were sung and glasses thumped on the bar.
酒馆里歌声阵阵，酒杯砰砰地顿在吧台上。
At ten o’clock father drove home along a lonely country road, made his horse comfortable for the night and himself went to bed, quite happy in his position in life.
十点钟，父亲沿着一条冷清的乡间小路赶车回家，把马安顿好，让它舒舒服服地过夜，自己便上床睡觉，对自己的身份地位相当满意。
He had at that time no notion of trying to rise in the world.
那时，他根本没有想过要设法出人头地。
It was in the spring of his thirty-fifth year that father married my mother, then a country school teacher, and in the following spring I came wriggling and crying into the world.
父亲是在他三十五岁那年春天娶的我母亲，母亲当时是一位乡村教师；到了第二年春天，我扭动着身子，哇哇哭着来到了这个世界。
Something happened to the two people.
这两个人身上起了某种变化。
They became ambitious.
他们变得野心勃勃。
The passion for getting up in the world took possession of them.
一股想要出人头地的狂热攫住了他们。
It may have been that mother was responsible.
这也许是母亲的缘故。
Being a school teacher she had no doubt read books and magazines.
身为学校教师，她想必读过书籍和杂志。
She had, I presume, read of how some people rose from poverty to fame and greatness and as I lay beside her—in the days of her lying-in—she may have dreamed that I would someday rule men and cities.
我猜想，她曾读到过有些人如何由贫寒起家，成就声名与伟业；我躺在她身边的时候——那是她坐月子的日子——她也许梦想过，有朝一日我会统治众人、主宰城市。
At any rate she induced father to give up his place as a farmhand, sell his horse and embark on an independent enterprise of his own.
不管怎样，她说动父亲辞掉了农场帮工的差事，卖掉了马，开始独立经营一份自己的事业。
She was a tall silent woman with a long nose and troubled grey eyes.
她是个高个子女人，沉默寡言，鼻子长长的，一双灰色的眼睛透着忧虑。
For herself she wanted nothing.
为自己，她一无所求。
For father and myself she was incurably ambitious.
为父亲和我，她的野心大得无可救药。
The first venture into which the two people went turned out badly.
两人投身的第一桩营生结果很糟。
They rented ten acres of poor stony land on Griggs’s Road, eight miles from Bidwell, and launched into chicken raising.
他们在离比德韦尔八英里的格里格斯路上租了十英亩贫瘠多石的土地，干起了养鸡这一行。
I grew into boyhood on the place and got my first impressions of life there.
我在那片农场上长成了少年，对人生最初的印象也是在那里形成的。
From the beginning they were impressions of disaster and if, in my turn, I am a gloomy man inclined to see the darker side of life, I attribute it to the fact that what should have been for me the happy joyous days of childhood were spent on a chicken farm.
从一开始，那些就是关于灾难的印象；如果说我也是个阴郁的人，倾向于看到人生较阴暗的一面，那么我把这归因于一个事实：本该是我快乐欢欣的童年时光，却是在一个养鸡场上度过的。
One unversed in such matters can have no notion of the many and tragic things that can happen to a chicken.
不谙此道的人根本想象不到，一只鸡可能遭遇的事有多少、有多悲惨。
It is born out of an egg, lives for a few weeks as a tiny fluffy thing such as you will see pictured on Easter cards, then becomes hideously naked, eats quantities of corn and meal bought by the sweat of your father’s brow, gets diseases called pip, cholera, and other names, stands looking with stupid eyes at the sun, becomes sick and dies.
它从蛋里出生，以小小的、毛茸茸的模样活上几个星期，就像你会在复活节贺卡上看到的画中那样，接着就变得光秃秃的，丑得吓人；它吃掉大量玉米和粗粉，那都是你父亲用汗水换来的；它会得上名叫禽舌病、霍乱以及别的名目的病；它站在那儿，两眼呆呆地望着太阳，接着病倒，死去。
A few hens and now and then a rooster, intended to serve God’s mysterious ends, struggle through to maturity.
少数几只母鸡，偶尔还有一只公鸡，本是要为上帝那神秘莫测的目的效力的，它们挣扎着活到成年。
The hens lay eggs out of which come other chickens and the dreadful cycle is thus made complete.
母鸡下蛋，蛋里又生出别的小鸡，这可怕的循环就这样完成了。
It is all unbelievably complex.
这一切复杂得令人难以置信。
Most philosophers must have been raised on chicken farms.
大多数哲学家想必都是在养鸡场里长大的。
One hopes for so much from a chicken and is so dreadfully disillusioned.
人对一只鸡指望那么多，幻灭起来又那么惨痛。
Small chickens, just setting out on the journey of life, look so bright and alert and they are in fact so dreadfully stupid.
小鸡刚刚踏上生命的旅程，看上去那么伶俐、那么机警，可实际上它们蠢得要命。
They are so much like people they mix one up in one’s judgments of life.
它们和人那么相像，以致把人弄糊涂了，让人对人生都判断不清。
If disease does not kill them they wait until your expectations are thoroughly aroused and then walk under the wheels of a wagon—to go squashed and dead back to their maker.
要是疾病没要了它们的命，它们就会一直等到你的期望被彻底吊起来，然后走到一辆大车的轮子底下——被轧得扁扁的，一命呜呼，回到造物主那里去。
Vermin infest their youth, and fortunes must be spent for curative powders.
它们幼小时害虫成灾，还得花大笔大笔的钱去买治病的药粉。
For ten years my father and mother struggled to make our chicken farm pay and then they gave up that struggle and began another.
十年间，父亲和母亲苦苦挣扎，想让我们的养鸡场赚钱；后来，他们放弃了这场挣扎，开始了另一场。
They decided to move into the town of Bidwell, and embarked in the restaurant business.
他们决定搬进比德韦尔镇，做起了餐馆生意。
After ten years of worry with incubators that did not hatch, and with tiny—and in their own way lovely—balls of fluff that passed on into semi-naked pullethood and from that into dead henhood, we threw all aside, packed our belongings on a wagon and drove down Griggs’s Road toward Bidwell, a tiny caravan of hope looking for a new place from which to start on our upward journey through life.
孵化器孵不出小鸡，一团团小小的绒球——它们自有其可爱之处——进入了半秃的小母鸡期，又从那里进入了死母鸡期；为这些操了十年心之后，我们把一切都抛到一边，把家当装上一辆大车，沿着格里格斯路朝比德韦尔驶去——一支小小的希望车队，要寻找一个新的地方，好从那里出发，踏上我们向上攀登的人生旅程。
We must have been a sad looking lot, not, I fancy, unlike refugees fleeing from a battlefield.
我们想必是一伙模样凄惨的人，依我看，和逃离战场的难民颇有几分相像。
Mother and I walked in the road.
母亲和我在路上步行。
The wagon that contained our goods had been borrowed for the day from Mr. Albert Griggs, a neighbor.
装着我们家什的那辆大车，是从邻居艾伯特·格里格斯先生那里借来用一天的。
Out of its sides stuck the legs of cheap chairs and at the back of the pile of beds, tables, and boxes filled with kitchen utensils was a crate of live chickens, and on top of that the baby carriage in which I had been wheeled about in my infancy.
车子两侧支棱出廉价椅子的腿；在那一堆床、桌子和装满厨房用具的箱子后部，放着一板条箱活鸡，箱子上面是那辆婴儿车，我还是婴儿时，就曾坐在里面被人推着到处走。
Why we stuck to the baby carriage I don’t know.
我们为什么死守着那辆婴儿车，我不知道。
It was unlikely other children would be born and the wheels were broken.
已经不大可能再有别的孩子出生，而且车轮也坏了。
People who have few possessions cling tightly to those they have.
财物很少的人，会把自己有的那点东西紧紧抓住不放。
That is one of the facts that make life so discouraging.
这便是使人生如此令人沮丧的事实之一。
Father rode on top of the wagon.
父亲坐在大车顶上。
He was then a bald-headed man of forty-five, a little fat and from long association with mother and the chickens he had become habitually silent and discouraged.
那时他是个四十五岁的秃顶男人，有点胖；由于长年和母亲以及那些鸡打交道，他已养成了沉默寡言、灰心丧气的习性。
All during our ten years on the chicken farm he had worked as a laborer on neighboring farms and most of the money he had earned had been spent for remedies to cure chicken diseases.
我们在养鸡场的整整十年里，他一直在邻近的农场当雇工，挣来的钱大部分都花在了治鸡病的药上。
There were two little patches of hair on father’s head just above his ears.
父亲的头上有两小片头发，就在耳朵上方。
I remember that as a child I used to sit looking at him when he had gone to sleep in a chair before the stove on Sunday afternoons in the winter.
我记得，小时候，每逢冬天的星期天下午，他在炉子前的椅子上睡着以后，我常常坐着看他。
I had at that time already begun to read books and have notions of my own and the bald path that led over the top of his head was, I fancied, something like a broad road, such a road as Caesar might have made on which to lead his legions out of Rome and into the wonders of an unknown world.
那时我已经开始读书，有了自己的想法；我觉得，从他头顶上越过的那条光秃秃的小道有点像一条宽阔的大路，就是恺撒或许会修筑的那种路，好让他率领自己的军团走出罗马，进入一个未知世界的种种奇观之中。
One might write a book concerning our flight from the chicken farm into town.
关于我们从养鸡场出逃进城的经过，或许可以写上一本书。
Mother and I walked the entire eight miles—she to be sure that nothing fell from the wagon and I to see the wonders of the world.
母亲和我走完了整整八英里——她是为了确保大车上没有东西掉下来，我则是为了看看世上的种种奇观。